<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Especiall obseruations, and approued physicall rules; which haue (heretofore) beene well tryed and experienced, in the last heauy and grieuous time of the pestilence And, vpon the good and benefit then ensuing by it: thought meete to bee now published, in this dangerous contagion of the plague. Seruing as soueraigne antidotes, for preseruation of all such as are not infected; as also for them that bee already visited.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855144</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855144</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1147:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Especiall obseruations, and approued physicall rules; which haue (heretofore) beene well tryed and experienced, in the last heauy and grieuous time of the pestilence And, vpon the good and benefit then ensuing by it: thought meete to bee now published, in this dangerous contagion of the plague. Seruing as soueraigne antidotes, for preseruation of all such as are not infected; as also for them that bee already visited.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Alsop and T. Fawcet, by the assigne of R. B[arker] and are to be sold at their house in Grubstreet, neere vnto the lower Pumpe25,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Especiall obseruations against the plague and pestilence.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plague --  Prevention --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20617:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Eſpeciall Obſeruations, AND APPROVED PHYSICALL RVLES; which haue (heretofore) beene well Tryed and Experienced, in the laſt heauy and grieuous time of the Peſtilence.</p>
            <p>AND, Vpon the Good and Benefit then enſuing by it: thought meete to bee now Publiſhed, in this dangerous Contagion of the Plague.</p>
            <p>SERVING <hi>As ſoueraigne Antidotes, for preſeruation</hi> of all ſuch as are not Infected; as alſo for them that bee already Viſited.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>B. Alſop</hi> and <hi>T. Fawcet,</hi> by the aſsignes of R.B. and are to be ſold at their Houſe in <hi>Grubſtreet,</hi> neere vnto the lower Pumpe, 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20617:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20617:2"/>
            <head>THE READERS DIRECTION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning this ſmal Trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe (gentle Reader) it hath beene entertained and allowed by very good Iudgements, both ſuch as haue beene deeply read in Phyſicke and Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, and haue made perfect experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, both in the Receits and Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Former times (of like fearefull Viſitation) haue found them ſollidly approued, euen vpon their beſt friends and familiars, whoſe welfare they ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as their owne. Yet I am not ſo raſh or indiſcreet, as to affirme theſe
<pb facs="tcp:20617:3"/> aduiſes of more ſecuritie, then either GODS aſsiſting Grace, or Mens beſt Practiſe may giue a bleſsing to. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this time of vrgent neceſsitie, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioneth the publiſhing for generall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit: <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, <hi>Apollo</hi> may water; but GOD onely is the ground, that giueth Grace and ſucceſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20617:3"/>
            <head>ESPECIALL OBSERVATONS, FIT TO BE VSED IN THE TIME OF PLAGVE AND PEST<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>LENCE.</head>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>With certaine Rules and good inſtructions, to be obſerued againſt the Plague, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as much as the force and infection of the diſeaſe called the Plague or Peſtilence, hath heretofore beene too well knowne, and now at this time is too fiercely felt in diuers and ſundry places of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and for that diuers Cities, Townes, and other places of this Realme, haue beene ſo grieuouſly vexed therewith: therefore (according to my ſimple skill and knowledge therein) I haue thought good to publiſh and make knowne vnto all, aſwell ſuch Preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues as are good to be vſed, obſerued and kept by all ſorts of people for the auoyding of the ſame diſeaſe, being greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious, and eaſily taken diuers and ſundry waies: as alſo for the better preſeruation of thoſe that are in health, from the infection of the diſeaſe, and to cure and order thoſe that are any way infected or grieued with the ſame: and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:20617:4"/> theſe things following, ought chiefly to be regarded, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued in all reſpects. (Viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To kéepe your Houſes, Yardes, Backſides, Stréetes, and Channells cleane from all ſtanding puddles, dunghils, and co, rupt moiſtures, which ingender ſtinking and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſauours that be noyſome, or may bréed infection.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To ſuffer no Dogs nor Cats to come into your houſes, nor to kéepe any your ſelues, (except you dwell in ſome open place of the Ayre) for they be very dangerous, and moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (of any kind of thing) to take infection of ſickneſſe, and to bring it home to their maiſters houſe; by reaſon that they run from place to place, and from one houſe to another, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually féeding vpon the vncleaneſt things that are caſt forth into the ſtréets.</p>
               <p n="3">3 To ayre your roomes (ſeuerally) with Char cole fire, made in ſtone pans, or Chaſing diſhes, and not in Chimneys; but as you can ſet your pans in the midſt of the Rome, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be ſure to ayre euery r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e twice a wéeke at the leaſt, and put into your fire, a little <hi>Frankenſcence, Iuniper,</hi> dryed <hi>Roſemary</hi> or <hi>Bay-leaues, Sage</hi> and <hi>Lauender.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 To waſh your linnen often, and to ayre your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Sun, or ouer pans of fire; or ouer a Chaſing diſh of Coales, and to fume the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me either with <hi>Frankenſcence,</hi> dryed <hi>Roſemary, Juniper,</hi> and <hi>Bay-leaues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 To ſmell to the Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te of <hi>Enula Campana,</hi> ſtéeped to white-Wine <hi>Vinegar,</hi> and wrapped in a handkerche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or elſe to <hi>Hearb grace,</hi> and <hi>Wormewood</hi> ſtéeped in <hi>Vinega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and carried either in the Mind of a <hi>Lemmon,</hi> or in ſome thing (made for that purpoſe cloſe ſtopt: Alſo powder of <hi>Enula-Campana</hi> rootes is drinke, or hanged about your neck, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chewed in your mouth is good. To eate or chew in your mouth either the rootes of <hi>Angelica, Setwall, Gentian, Valerian, Cinamon,</hi> or the rootes of <hi>Aras,</hi> and to vſe euery Morning faſting to eate <hi>Sorrell</hi> ſtéeped in <hi>Vinegar,</hi> with a little bread and butter; or if vinegar be ſcarſe, then with <hi>Sorrell</hi> ſauce. Alſo to eat a kernell of a <hi>Walnut</hi> mixt with 5. or 6. loaues of
<pb facs="tcp:20617:4"/> 
                  <hi>Herbegrace,</hi> and a corne or two of Salt, put altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Fig warmed, and eaten faſting twice or thrice a wéeke, and to faſt thrée houres after it.</p>
               <p n="6">6 To comfort the ſtomack, often with an <hi>Alebery</hi> made of <hi>Cloues, Mace, Nutmegs, Saunders, Genny Greines,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="7">7 To drinke <hi>Rue, Wormewood</hi> and <hi>Scabious,</hi> ſtéep't in <hi>Ale</hi> a whole night, in the morning faſting: (alſo to take the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es of <hi>Enula Campana</hi> beaten together and drinke faſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing) or to drinke the powder of <hi>Turmentill</hi> in <hi>Sortell</hi> or <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious Water</hi> faſting: or elſe to take the water of <hi>Cardus Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictus,</hi> or <hi>Angelica</hi> mixt with <hi>Methridatum.</hi> Alſo <hi>Bay-Berries</hi> huskt before they be drie beaten to powder, and drinke it either in ſtale <hi>Beere</hi> or <hi>Ale,</hi> or in <hi>Wine,</hi> and to ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t vpon it and to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare ſléepe.</p>
               <p n="8">8 To procure ſweat being in your naked bed, by drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Poſſet Ale,</hi> ſodden with <hi>Sorrell</hi> and <hi>Burrage</hi> and mixt with <hi>Triacle,</hi> but if any féele the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſelues infected, let them take <hi>Angelica water</hi> mixt with <hi>Methridatum,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, ſweat in bed vpon it.</p>
               <p n="9">9 To preſerue your ſelues by correcting the ayre in your houſes, It is neceſſary that you take <hi>Roſemary,</hi> drie <hi>Iuniper, Bay-leaues,</hi> or <hi>Frankenſcence,</hi> and caſt the ſame vpon a Chaſing diſh of coales, and receiue the ſmoke or fume there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into your head, if you haue it, you may put a little Lauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as <hi>Sage</hi> that is dryed into the fire with the reſt, and it will be the better.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Alſo to preſerue your ſelues otherwiſe by perfuming or correcting the Ayre in your houſes and Chambers: Take a good quantity of <hi>Wine Vineger,</hi> and put thereto a little <hi>Roſewater,</hi> and 10. or 12. branches of <hi>Roſemary,</hi> and put them all into the Baſon: then take 5. or 6. <hi>Flintſtones,</hi> and heate them red hot in the fire, and caſt them into the ſaid Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſo perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e your Chambers or other R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es therewith as often as you ſhall thinke méete, and let them be ſo done one after another.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20617:5"/>11 Likewiſe to preſerue your ſelfe by perfuming of your Apparell: take the ſame apparell that you doe vſually weare and let the ſame bée kept ſwéete and cleane, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume it often, either with r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Saunders</hi> burnt, or elſe with <hi>Iuniper:</hi> And if you happen to be with any that are in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, aſſoone as euer you come home, ſhift your ſelfe immediately, and ayre your cloathes as aforeſaid, or otherwiſe ayre them well in ſome open Ayre.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Laſtly, if the patient be coſtiue, and hard bound in his belly, then let him take a Suppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tarie made with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle boyled <hi>Hunny,</hi> and a little fine powder of Salt, and ſo take it in at the Fundament, and ſo let it be kept therein till it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> a ſtoole or two.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipes">
               <head>PRESER<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ATIVES (Corporall) againſt the Plague and Peſtilence.</head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A moſt ſingular good preſeruatiue to bee taken againſt all manner of bad and corrupt Ayres, in places infected.</head>
                  <p>TAke a handfull of <hi>Sage.</hi> and ſéethe it in a gallon of fayre running <hi>Water,</hi> and let it ſéethe vntill the one halfe be conſumed, then couer it cloſe and ſet it ouer the fire againe, and put into it a good quantitie of <hi>Hunny,</hi> and as much <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> and then ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it tl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, and put it into a glaſſe, and ſtop it cloſe, and when you will vſe it, drinke 5. or 6. ſpoonefulls of it faſting, and it will preſerue you from taking of any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Ayres all the day after whereſoeuer you goe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20617:5"/>
                  <head>Another good preſeruatiue to be vſed againſt the Plague when you goe into an open ayre, or elſe where common aſſemblies are.</head>
                  <p>TAke a ſpunge and dip it in <hi>Vinegar</hi> and <hi>Roſe-wate</hi> min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, or elſe in <hi>Vinegar</hi> wherein <hi>Wormewood</hi> or <hi>Rue</hi> haue béene boyled in, and vſe to ſmell often thereto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An excellent Pomander to be vſed againſt the ill ſauoured ſent of the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke the quantitie of 4. pound of <hi>Olibanum Labeanum,</hi> and put to it a pound weight of the ſtrongeſt <hi>Vinegar</hi> that may be gotten, and ſet them to ſeethe in an earthen pot for a good ſpace, then take the quantitie of a pound of pure yellow <hi>Wax,</hi> and a little <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and let them be ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and bruiſed together in a braſſe Morter, &amp; then put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 3. or 4. ounces of <hi>Storax Liquida,</hi> and let it bee made thicke like vnto paſte, and ſo make thy pomanders, and if thou wilt haue the ſame ſwéeter, then put therein halfe an ounce of <hi>Spikenard,</hi> and of <hi>Cloues</hi> beaten to powder and <hi>Muske Roſes,</hi> of each of them 2. ounces, and of <hi>Camphire</hi> a dram, and ſo make it vp at pleaſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke fine <hi>Cinamon, Cloues, Amber, Nutmeg, Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Camomill, Iuniper</hi> and <hi>Red Roſes,</hi> and beate them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, and make a powder thereof, and then mingle the ſame with <hi>Roſe water</hi> and ſo make a pomander thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A ſpeciall good d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inke to be v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed of all ſuch as are g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d with the Plague or Peſtilence, during all the time of their ſickneſſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quarter of an ounce of great <hi>Valerian,</hi> a handfull of <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ell,</hi> and an ounce of the Rootes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Butter-burie,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Peſtilent-wort</hi>) and bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le them in fayre Running <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>White-win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of either like much from a quart to a pint, and ſtraine it and put th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reto two ſpoonfulls of <hi>Vinegar,</hi> and two ounces of fine <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er,</hi> and then boyle them againe, and then let the party grieues drinke a good draught thereof as hot as poſſibly he may abide it, and if he
<pb facs="tcp:20617:6"/> hap to caſt it vp againe, then let him drinke the like draught immediately vpon it, and prouoke himſelfe to ſweate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A ſpeciall good Preſeruatiue againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke an <hi>Egge</hi> and make a hole in the top of it, then take out both the Yolke and White, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll the ſhell with the waight of 2. French Crowns of Engliſh <hi>Saffron,</hi> &amp; then roaſt the Shell and <hi>Saffron</hi> together in the Embers of Charcoles, vntill the ſhell were yellow, then beate them together in a morter with halfe a ſpoonfull of <hi>Muſtard-ſeed,</hi> and as ſoone as any ſuſpition is had of iuſtation, diſſolue the weight of a French crowne in 10. ſpoonfulls of <hi>Poſſet-ale,</hi> &amp; let the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent drinke it luke warme, and ſweate vpon it in naked bed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a handfull of <hi>Herbe-grace</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Rue</hi> and <hi>Sorrell</hi> of either a handfull, of <hi>Elder leaues,</hi> a handfull of <hi>Red Sage,</hi> and a handfull of <hi>Red Bramble leaues,</hi> and ſtampe them well together, and ſtraine them through a fine cloth, with a quart of <hi>White-wine,</hi> then take a good quantity of <hi>Caſe-Ginger</hi> and mingle it well with them, and drinke a good draught thereof both Morning and Euening, for the ſpace of 9. daies together, and by Gods grace it will preſerue you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of <hi>Garlicke,</hi> and pill it, and mince it ſmall, and boyle it in new milke, and eate it euery Morning faſting. <hi>This hath beene truly proued.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke 2. <hi>Figges,</hi> 2. <hi>Walnuts,</hi> 20. <hi>Leaues</hi> of <hi>Rue,</hi> and a dram of <hi>Salt,</hi> and ſtampe them all very well together, and eate them faſting, and it will preſerue you all the day after: as well againſt the Plague, as alſo againſt any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poyſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Alloes Hepatica,</hi> pure <hi>Cinamon</hi> and <hi>Mirrh,</hi> of each of them thrée drams, of <hi>Cloues, Mace,</hi> wood of <hi>Alloes,</hi> (commonly call <hi>Lignum Alloes, Maſticke</hi> and <hi>Bole Orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi> of each of them one ounce, mixe them together, and make
<pb facs="tcp:20617:6"/> them into a fine powder, and drinke the ſame faſting euery Morning, either in white <hi>Wine</hi> delayed with water, or elſe with <hi>Ale,</hi> (but if it be with <hi>Wine,</hi> mingle it with a little water, but mingle nothing with the <hi>Ale,</hi> and by Gods helpe this will preſerue you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good Preſeruatiue vſed by Methridates.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Figges</hi> which are not worme-eaten, and waſh them cleane, and of the kernels of <hi>Walnuts</hi> cleane picked, of each of them an 100. the weight of foure pence of <hi>Salt,</hi> and of the leaues of <hi>Hearb-Grace</hi> the weight of 2. ſhillings. Then take the Figs and the kernels of the Walnuts, and cut them in pieces, and ſtamp them well, &amp; then put the Leaues vnto them, and ſtir them very well together, and then ſtraint the Salt with the reſt, and ſtir it vntill it be incorporated, and made of one ſubſtance, then put it into ſome Earthen pot or <hi>Gallipot,</hi> wherein it may be kept both ſwéet and cleane, and when occaſion ſerueth for vſe thereof: take the quantitie of 2. or 3. Figs thereof, and eate it euery morning faſting, and by Gods helpe it will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> preſerue you. <hi>If you giue it to young children, the one halfe of the ſame will ſerue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame. An excellent good Medicine againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke an ounce of the leaues of <hi>Hearb-grace,</hi> halfe an ounce of good <hi>Figs,</hi> an ounce of <hi>Iuniper berries,</hi> 2. ounces of <hi>Walnuts</hi> cleane picked, 4, ounces of Wine <hi>Vinegar,</hi> and a good quantity of <hi>Saffron,</hi> and ſtampe them all together, and then put them into a glaſſe or Earthen pot that is clean, and ſtop it cloſe that no ayre may iſſue forth of it, and when you haue occaſion to vſe it, then take it out either vpon a kniues point (or ſome other inſtrument fit for that purpoſe) the quantity of a Beane or ſomewhat more, and eate the ſame in the morning faſting, and by Gods helpe you ſhall be ſure not to be infected with the Plague, for the ſpace of 24. houres, after the taking thereof, and you ſhall finde that it will doe the Patient excéeding much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20617:7"/>
                  <head>A ſoueraigne Drinke (if it be taken in time) to preſerue one againſt the Plague or Peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>TAke the quantity of a dram and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> halfe of <hi>Powder Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall,</hi> a dram of <hi>Triacle</hi> and of <hi>Dragon Water,</hi> and <hi>Sorrell water,</hi> of each of them an oz. and drinke it with <hi>Ale</hi> in the Morning faſting, (and if one haue taken the infection within 24. houres before, yet by Gods grace he ſhall eſcape it. <hi>This hath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly proued in the laſt great viſitation, and hath done much good.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Hearbegrace, Sage</hi> of vertue, <hi>red Bramble Leaues,</hi> and <hi>Elder leaues,</hi> of each of them a good handfull, ſtampe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> altogether and ſtraine them through a fine linnen cloth with a quart of the beſt old white <hi>Wine</hi> that may be gotten and put therein 3. penyworth of pure good <hi>Ginger</hi> finely bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to powder, and let any one (fearing or miſdoubting the Plague) drinke euery Morning faſting a good ſpoonfull of it, and let him or her vſe it for the ſpace of 10. or 12. dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and it will doe (by Gods grace) excéeding much good, for this hath béene holden an excellent good preſeruatiue againſt the infection of the Plague.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good preſeruatiue againſt the Plague or Peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Scabious</hi> and <hi>Morſis Diaboli,</hi> of each of them ſuch a quantitie as to your owne iudgement ſhall bée thought méet, ſtampe them very well, and then ſtraine them, and then take the iuyce of them, and ſet it vpon the fire, and then you ſhall perceiue a gréene curde to ariſe vpon the top of it, but ſcumme that off as cleane as you can then take the cléere liquor, and put into it thré<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quarters of a pound of the fineſt white <hi>Sugar</hi> that may be had, and ſo let it ſéethe vntill the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> halfe of the liquor be conſumed, then take it off, and ſo kéep it ſafe, and when occaſion ſerueth, let the party take the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thrée ſpoonefulls thereof at a time, both Morning and Euening (luke warme) and this will preſerue one greatly. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20617:7"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Butter-milke</hi> and eate thereof euery day during the time of ſickneſſe, and it will doe you much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke 5. ſpoonfulls of <hi>Wine-Vinegar</hi> 3. ſpoonefulls of faire Running <hi>water.</hi> di. a ſpoonfull of <hi>Triacle</hi> of <hi>Iene</hi> and of <hi>Bole Armoniacke,</hi> as much as a ſmall <hi>Nut</hi> (it being beaten to ſmall powder) and drinke it euery Morning and Euening. <hi>Proued by M. K. of An.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke 7. or 8. leaues of <hi>Sorrell,</hi> and waſh them in faire <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>Vinegar,</hi> and ſtéepe them in the ſaid <hi>Water,</hi> and <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> a good while and eate them faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke the fineſt and pureſt <hi>Alloes</hi> that may be gotten, and of <hi>Cinamon</hi> and <hi>Mirh,</hi> of each of them the weight of 3. French Crownes (or the weight of 2. pence in ſiluer) and of <hi>Lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Aloes, Cloues, Mace, Maſticke,</hi> and <hi>Bole Orientall,</hi> of each of them di. an oz. mingle them together, and beate them into fine powder: then take the weight of 4. pence thereof, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay it into white <hi>Wine</hi> and faire <hi>Water,</hi> and ſo drinke it euery Morning faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An excellent good Drinke to be taken euery morning for a preſeruatiue againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good handfull of <hi>Winter-Sauery,</hi> and boyle it in a quart of good Wine <hi>Vinegar,</hi> with a ſpoonfull of <hi>Greines</hi> (being beaten and put into it:) and put thereto a good quantity of fine <hi>Sugar,</hi> and take a good draught thereof euery morning faſting. Alſo if you muſt of neceſſary came into any place where any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious perſons are, then it is good for you to ſmell to the Root of <hi>Angelica, Gentian,</hi> or <hi>Valerian,</hi> and to chew any of theſe in your mouth, and you ſhall finde much vertue in them. <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A maruellous good Medicine for the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke 3. or 4. ſlips of <hi>Herbe-grace,</hi> and 6. ſpoonfulls of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and beate them both together in a Morter, then ſtraine out the iuyce of it cloane, and put thereto an ounce
<pb facs="tcp:20617:8"/> of pure <hi>Triacle,</hi> and an ounce of fine <hi>Suger,</hi> and ſet it on the fire, and ſtirre it well t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ether, and make thereof a Sirop, and then put it into a cloſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and when you will vſe it, take a <hi>Sage</hi> leafe and ſpread as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h as a Beane of the ſame vpon the leafe, and ſo eate it euery Morning and Euening, and it will doe you much good. Alſo if any one bee infected and vſe this often, it will quite expell the Plague from his heart: but if hée be not infected, it will preſerue him within the ſpace of 24. houres after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke euery Morning faſting, a dry <hi>Fig,</hi> a <hi>Walnut,</hi> and 4. or 5. leaues of <hi>Hearbe-grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and chop them altogether very ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all and eate them, and afterwards drinke a good draught of White or Claret <hi>Wine:</hi> but if it bée a woman with Child, leaue out the <hi>Hearbe-grace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pinte of <hi>Honey,</hi> a quarter of a pound of <hi>Bole Armoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke,</hi> and as much <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>anguis Draconis,</hi> and as much of <hi>Terra ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillata,</hi> halfe an ounce of <hi>Cloues</hi> and a pinte of <hi>Aq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a vitae</hi> and ſeethe them all together, vntill they bée all as th cke as pap, and when you will vſe it, take the quantity of a ſpoonfull thereof firſt and laſt, but take héed that you doe neither walke nor drinke, for the ſpace of an houre after the taking thereof, and this will doe you maruellous much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A good Preſeruatiue for a Woman with Child, or ſuch as are delicate or tender, that cannot away with taking of Medicines.</head>
                  <p>TAke a toſt of <hi>White</hi> or <hi>Wheat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ead,</hi> and ſprinkle thereat a little powder of <hi>Cinamon,</hi> and eate it in the Morning faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But if <hi>Cinamon</hi> or <hi>Vineger</hi> be not to be had: then you may eate <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ead</hi> and <hi>Butter</hi> alone, for <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>utter</hi> is not onely a preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue againſt the Plague: but alſo againſt all other venome and poyſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An excellent good Medicine to bee drunke, ſuſpecting your ſelfe to bee Infected.</head>
                  <p>TAke a great <hi>Onion</hi> and take forth the <hi>Core,</hi> then fill it full a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with <hi>Triacle</hi> of <hi>Iene,</hi> and wrap the ſame in a péece of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb facs="tcp:20617:8"/> and toaſt it vntill it be ſoft, and then ſtraine it with a little <hi>White Wine Vineger,</hi> and temper it with a pretty quantitie of <hi>Sugar,</hi> and giue the patient two ſpoonefuls thereof to drinke fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and if he bée infected with the Plague, it will bée perceiued within ſixe houres after the receipt of the ſame drinke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good preſeruatiue againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Rootes</hi> of <hi>Bayes, May-weede</hi> (both leaues and rootes) of each of them a like quantitie, a good quantitie of <hi>Triacle</hi> of <hi>Iene,</hi> and a ſmall quantitie of <hi>Dragon Rootes</hi> and <hi>Leaues,</hi> and mingle them well together with <hi>Ale</hi> and make a Poſſet thereof, and ſo vſe to drinke dayly thereof, and you ſhall finde great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thereby.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another preſeruatiue againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke a <hi>Figge,</hi> and put therein a little <hi>Hea b-Grace</hi> bruiſed, and mingled with a little <hi>Bay Salt</hi> beaten ſmall, and the <hi>Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi> of a <hi>Walnut</hi> cleane picked, and let the patient vſe euery Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to eate thrée or foure of theſe Figs thus ordred faſting, and let him drinke a good draught of Wine or Béere afterwards, and then walke an houre after it, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e eate any meate, and ſo by vſing of this euery Morning as aforeſaid, by Gods helpe he ſhall be ſafe from any infection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Wormwood</hi> and <hi>Rue,</hi> of each of them a handfull, and bruiſe them a little, and put them into an Earthen or pewter pot, with as much white Wine <hi>Vineger</hi> as will couer the hearbes, and kéepe it cloſe ſtopt, and when you feare any infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, dip a little péece of a ſpunge into the Vineger, and then put it either into a round Ball made of <hi>Iuory</hi> or <hi>Iuniper,</hi> with little hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s on the top, or elſe the Rinde of a <hi>Lemmon,</hi> beeing opened on the top, and all the ſubſtance taken f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rth and carry it in your hand as you goe in the ſtreets, and ſo vſe to ſmell often vnto it, and this will preſerue you greatly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another excellent good p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſeruatiue againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke halfe an hundred of <hi>Greene Walnuts,</hi> (being new ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken off, as they hang greene on the Tree) a pound of the inner <hi>Barke</hi> of an <hi>Aſh-tree,</hi> and of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ttymorrell, Houſleeke, Scabious,</hi> and <hi>Veruaine,</hi> of each of them a handfull and
<pb facs="tcp:20617:9"/> halfe an oz. of <hi>Saffron,</hi> and mince them altogether, and put a pottle of the ſtrongeſt <hi>Vinegar</hi> to them that may be gotten, and boyle them ouer the fire in a pot cloſe ſtopt, and afterwards di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill them in a Lymbecke: then take the ſame water, and kéepe it in a Glaſſe, and when occaſion ſerueth for vſe thereof, drinke 4. or 5. ounces thereof at a time, and ſo vſe to take it 4. times in 24. houres ſpace, and when you doe take it, be ſure to be in your naked bed, and prouoke your body to ſweate, and in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you ſhall ſuſtaine great comfort both to heart and body. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good Preſeruatiue for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke tenne graines of powder of <hi>Saff on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> twenty <hi>Greines</hi> of the Kernels of <hi>Walnuts</hi> cleane picked, two or three <hi>Greines</hi> of <hi>Figges,</hi> three <hi>Greines</hi> of <hi>Meth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>datum,</hi> one oz. of <hi>Pimpernell Water,</hi> and ſixe <hi>Sage leaues:</hi> ſtampe all theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and put it into a cloſe glaſſe, and eate thereof euery morning faſting the quantiti. of 12, <hi>Graines,</hi> and this by Gods helpe will preſerue you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of <hi>Rue,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Hearbgrace</hi>) or <hi>Wormewood</hi> (or both if you pleaſe) and put it into a pot of vſuall drinke, and let it ſtéepe for the ſpace of a whole night, cloſe ſtopped, and drinke thereof in the Morning faſting, and by often vſing of it, it will both purge the blood and preſerue you from the diſeaſe: Alſo if you take 7. or 8. <hi>Berries</hi> of <hi>Iuniper</hi> dryed, and made into fine powder, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd put the ſame into your drinke, wherein the <hi>Rue</hi> and <hi>Wormewood</hi> hath béene ſtéeped as aforeſaid, it will be much the better, and of a farre greater vertue: but if you cannot get any <hi>Iuniper Berries</hi> then take a little powder of <hi>Wormewo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d,</hi> and powder of <hi>Valerian,</hi> and vſe it in your drinke as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke powder of <hi>Turmentill</hi> the weight of <hi>6.</hi> pence either in <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>Scabious</hi> or in <hi>Sorrell water</hi> in the Summer, but if it be in the Winter: then take it with Water of <hi>Valerian,</hi> (if it may be gotten) or elſe with ſome other ordinary drinke, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ece of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:20617:9"/> Roote, kept in your mouth, as you walke in the ſtreetes, is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous good and Cordiall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Rue, Mandrago is, Fetherfew, Burnet,</hi> and <hi>Sorrell,</hi> of each of them halfe a handfull, and a good quantity of crops and rootes of <hi>Dragons,</hi> waſh them all very cleane, and ſeethe them on a ſoft fire in faire running <hi>Water,</hi> from a pottle to a quart: then ſtraine them through a fine linnen cloth, and if it be bitter, put thereto as much <hi>Sugar Candie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> as will make it ſweet, or elſe ſome other fine <hi>Sugar,</hi> and if this Medicine he miniſtred before the Purples doe ariſe, it will helpe, but it muſt be taken euery morning faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An exceeding good Medicine to be taken againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke an oz. of the leaues of <hi>Herbe Grace,</hi> halfe on oz. of good <hi>Figges</hi> an oz. of <hi>uniper berries,</hi> 2. ounces of <hi>Walnuts</hi> cleane picked, 4. ounces of <hi>Wine Vineg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and a good quantity of <hi>Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron,</hi> and ſtampe them altoge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her, and put them in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o an Earthen Pot or Glaſſe, and ſtop it cloſe that no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yre may iſſue out, then take ſome of it forth vpon a kniues point, or elſe with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtrument to the quantitie of a Beane or more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e it in the Morning faſting, and by Gods grace, it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll preſerue you from infection for 24. houres after the taking of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Betony water,</hi> and white <hi>Wine Vineg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r,</hi> of each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f them 3. ſpoonefuls, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd the quantitie of a <hi>N t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eg</hi> of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> of <hi>Iene,</hi> or elſe the quantitie of a haſte Nut of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tum,</hi> and mingle them altogether, and let the ſicke perſon take it in the beginning of his ſickneſſe, and this will doe him exceeding much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a b Grace, Southernwood, Mugwoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t,</hi> and <hi>Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> of each of them a handfull, and 3. or 4. handfuls of <hi>Iuniper Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rie</hi> which are blacke, and then cut and ſhred the hearbes very ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all, and put them into an Earthen Pot or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kin, and put to them a gallon of white <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Vinegar,</hi> and let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20617:10"/> they be greene, then let them not ſoke aboue 14. houres) then take a handfull or two of the ſame hearbs forth, and put them into a Still, and then put therein a quart of the ſame <hi>Vinegar,</hi> and ſo diſtill them with a ſoft fire, (for ouermuch fire will waſte it, and when it is diſtilled, put as much more as aforeſaid into the Still, and ſo doe vntill you haue diſtilled all. That being d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e, put it into a Pipkin or earthen veſſel againe, and then put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>erein as many of the ſame hearbes freſh now againe as you did before, and then let them ſoke for the ſpace of 7. or 8. dayes and nights more, and then diſtill them againe (as you did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) and ſo vſe the hearbs and Berries, the third time againe as you did twi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e before: and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> put into the Pipkin 4. ounces of pure and good <hi>Methridatum,</hi> amonſt the hearbes, or if it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had, take 6. or 7. ounces of good <hi>Triacle,</hi> and put therein: and when it is well diſtilled, put it into a double Glaſſe, and ſtop it cloſe, and binde a piece of cleane Leather about the top of it, and ſo keepe it cloſe, and when occaſion ſerueth for vſe thereof, and that you perceiue any one to bee infected with the Plague; then giue him that is grieued 4. ounces t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ereof at a time, but if it be a woman, giue her not aboue 3. ounces, and to a childe according to the age, and as the childe is able to beare it, and let him or her that ſo taketh it, ſweat vpon it for the ſpace of 3. or 4. houres after the taking thereof, but if the patient be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to indure it, let him ſweat longer, and let ſome body ſtand alwaies by the ſicke perſon, to dry the ſweat from his face, leaſt that by putting of his or her hands out of the bed, cold be taken, and more danger of death enſue thereby, and with all doubt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by Gods helpe, this will yéeld him comfort and helpe in a ſhort ſpace. This is a maruellous good Medicine, and hath béene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times of late experienced: this is alſo good againſt the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, being much vſed as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An excellent good drinke, generally to be vſed for all ſorts of people, that are infected with the Plague, and to be made with ſmall coſt.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Burrage Burnet,</hi> and <hi>Marigolds</hi> (which are of a browne col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur) of each of them a good handfull: then take 9. or 10. crops of the youngeſt <hi>Roſemari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and boyle all theſe together
<pb facs="tcp:20617:10"/> in a quart of ſtale <hi>Ale</hi> clarified: then put therein a little whole <hi>Mace,</hi> and a pretty quantity of fine <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r,</hi> and a cruſt of <hi>White</hi> or <hi>Wheaten Bread,</hi> and let the ſicke perſon drinke of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all the time of his or her ſickneſſe, and this will bee moſt comfortable and good.</p>
                  <p>Alſo vſe to put <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>pernell</hi> in the ſicke perſons broth, that you doe commonly make for him either to ſup or eate, and it will be the better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good Drinke to be vſed to thoſe that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ies</hi> of <hi>Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> (that are ripe) (gathered on the North ſide of the tree, and dry them in the ſhadow: and then ſtamp them to powder: then take d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. a dram of the ſame powder, and temper it well with 2. ounces of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntine Water,</hi> and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea the ſicke perſon is deſirous to drinke, let him take a good drang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thereof: and let him remaine in his bed, and ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t as much and as of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n as he can, after he hath taken it, then warme a cleane ſhirt for him and put it on, and if his ſhirts may be ſhif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, it will be the better after his ſweating and likewiſe his ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes and clothes, and in vſing of this for the ſpace of 3. dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he will either dye or mend without all doubt (by Gods helpe.) <hi>This hath beene truely prou d.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another precious Drinke for one infected with the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Fetherfew, Matfellen, Mugwoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, Solſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>Mallowes,</hi> of each of them alike quantity, waſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> cleaue, and ſtampe them, and temper them well with ſtale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and giue it the ſicke perſon to drinke, (the quanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ſpoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulls thereof at a time) and if it be taken in time, it will both deſtroy the corruption: and alſo keepe the ſicke perſon from all danger of death. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of <hi>Scabious water</hi> and <hi>Betony water,</hi> and mingle them together with a good quantite of <hi>Triacl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>leane,</hi> and giue it the Patient to drinke immediately af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter that hee ſuſpecteth himſelfe to bee infected. And if it happen that the ſicke perſon finde himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe greatly grieued, and that any ſwelling begin in any place to grow ſore, then
<pb facs="tcp:20617:11"/> take <hi>Elder-leaues, Red Bramble leaues,</hi> and <hi>Muſtardſeed,</hi> and ſtampe them altogether, and make a Plaiſter thereof, and lay the ſame to the ſore, and this will both drawe and heale.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good drinke to be made and vſed for the ſame purpoſe, or otherwiſe, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>TAke 3. ounces of <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and an oz. and an halfe of <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> and put 3. drams of perfect good <hi>Cinamon,</hi> and a dram of Yellow <hi>Saunders</hi> to ſteepe therein, and when it is well ſteeped, then ſtraine it through a hayre Strainer, and ſwéeten it well with the conſerues of <hi>Roſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and when occaſion ſerueth for vſe thereof, take the quantity of an oz. thereof at a time, and giue it the ſicke perſon in the Morning faſting, or elſe make a toſt of fine Manchet, or Wheaten bread, and ſoke the toſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and it will doe him much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good Drink to be vſed in the time of Viſitation.</head>
                  <p>TAke 5. ſpoonefulls of <hi>Dragon water,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ſpoonefulls of the ſtrongeſt white <hi>Wine Vinegar</hi> that may bee gotten, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. a ſpoonefull of <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iacle</hi> of <hi>Iene,</hi> a quarter of a ſpoonfull of <hi>Bole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacke,</hi> beaten into fine powder, and as much or ſomewhat more of the roote of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>etwall</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> likewiſe beaten to powder, and when any one is infected (or elſe not) and when he taketh it, let him faſt from both meat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and drinke for the ſpace of 12. houres after, vnleſſe he thinke good to take of the ſame drinke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and he ſhall receiue great comfort thereby. But if you can get any powder <hi>Imperiall,</hi> put in a like quantitie as of the reſt, and it will bee the better, this muſt be taken alwayes blood warme, and as often as you ſhall thinke conuenient your ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke an <hi>Onion,</hi> and make a hole in it, and take out the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Core,</hi> then take <hi>Dragon Water, Triacle</hi> and <hi>Pepper,</hi> (bruiſed) and put them altogether into the <hi>Onion,</hi> and roaſt them in the embers, and then bruiſe it and ſtraine it with purt <hi>Malmſie,</hi> and giue it the Patient to drinke. <hi>This is a preſent remedie, if it bee taken before the heart bee infected. Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20617:11"/>
                  <head>A good Medicine to prouoke ſleepe to the ſicke perſon.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity of <hi>Womans breſt Milke,</hi> and put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a like quantity of <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> ſtirre them well together, and moiſten the temples of the head of the patient, and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthrils well t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erewith, and let it be laid on with ſome feather, or with ſome fine linnen cloth, and this will doe much good. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A Maruellous good drinke for them that are infected with the Plague or Peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>TAke 2. handfulls of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rell</hi> and a handfull of <hi>Violet leaues,</hi> and a bunch of ſower <hi>Grap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> and beate all theſe together, (ſtalkes and all) then ſtraine them with <hi>Buttermilke,</hi> and make a Poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t of the ſame, and let the ſicke perſon drinke as much thereof as you ſhall thinke good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good drinke for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Leafe-Gold,</hi> and mingle it with the iuyce of <hi>Lemmons,</hi> and a little <hi>Sug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> candie, Cloues M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce,</hi> and a little quanti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Liquor ce</hi> finely pared, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liced, and let all theſe bee ſteeped in <hi>White wine,</hi> or elſe in good <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> wine,</hi> and put there in a good quantity of the powder of <hi>Angell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> or e ſe of the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tion</hi> of the ſame roote, and let the party grieued drinke this warme, and it will doe him maruelous much good. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another excellent good drinke for the ſicke perſon.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Cardus Benedictus, Red Sage, Hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and <hi>Red B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ble leaues,</hi> of each of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> a like qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie, and ſtampe them altogether in a Morter, and ſtrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> through a fine linnen cloth, with a quart of <hi>White w n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and let the ſicke perſon drinke 5. or 6. ſpoonefulls euery day; but if it be taken, and vſed often before infection, it will preſerue one from the Plague a long ſpace after, <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A ſoueraigne Drinke for any infected perſon.</head>
                  <p>TAke a péece of fine <hi>Gold,</hi> or the leaues of pure beaten <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ld,</hi> and put it into the iuyce of <hi>Lemmons</hi> and let it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> therin for the ſpace of 24. houres, then take the ſame iuyce, and put to it a little powder of <hi>Angelica Rootes,</hi> and then mingle them with white <hi>Wine,</hi> and let the patient drinke a good draught thereof.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20617:12"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is a moſt pretious drinke, and it is greatly to be wondred at, what helpe and remedy ſome that haue vſed this drinke haue had thereby, although it hath beene ſuppoſed by many learned Phyſitions, that the ſicke perſons were paſt all hope of remedy: yet by Gods prouidence they haue recouered againe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good drinke to be taken, either before or after Infection.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Betony water</hi> and <hi>Scabious water,</hi> of each of them a good quantity, and a good quantitie of fine <hi>Triacle,</hi> and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per them well together, and let the patient drinke it, and it will expell the venome or poyſon cleaue forth. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good drinke for one being infected.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Cardus Benedictus</hi> and diſtill it, and <hi>Centorie,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill it likewiſe, and mingle the two waters together, and let the ſicke perſon drinke a good draught thereof with <hi>Triacle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and it will doe him maruellous much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An excellent good drinke for the Plague, if it be taken in time.</head>
                  <p>TAke a dram of <hi>Methridatum,</hi> and giue it the patient with <hi>Dragon water, White Wine,</hi> or other liquor, to drinke when he ſuppoſeth himſelfe infected firſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An excellent good Poulteſſe to ripen and bring forth the ſore.</head>
                  <p>TAke a white <hi>Onion,</hi> and cut it in pieces, and thrée ounces of <hi>Butter</hi> that is cleane without ſalt, and the weight of 20. pence of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eauen,</hi> and a little <hi>Otemeale</hi> ſmall beaten, then boyle theſe together with a little new <hi>Milke,</hi> or elſe <hi>Water,</hi> and make a Poulteſſe thereof, and lay it very warme to the ſore, and it will ripen it ſuddenly. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>IF the Botch happen to appeare, then take a good quantitie of <hi>Elder leaues, Red Bramble leaues,</hi> and <hi>Muſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dſeed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtamp them well together, and make a Plaiſter therof and apply it to the ſore, and it will draw forth all the venome and corruption.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20617:12"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a handfull of <hi>Smalladge,</hi> or <hi>Louage,</hi> if you can get it, and two handfulls of <hi>Valerian,</hi> and two or thrée rootes of <hi>Dane-wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t</hi> and ſeethe them all in faire running Water, and freſh <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er,</hi> and put thereto a few crums of wheaten <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ead,</hi> and make a Poulteſſe thereof, and lay it warme to the ſore, and ſo let it remaine there vntill it breake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Anothe experienced Medicine for the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke a <hi>Cocke,</hi> a <hi>Chicken,</hi> or a <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t,</hi> and pull all the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of the tayle, ſo that the Rumpe may be bare, and then hold the Rumpe or bare place to the ſore, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ately you ſhall ſee the Cocke, Chicken or Pullet gape, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for life, and in the end it will dye: Then take another Cocke, Chicken, or Pullet againe and doe the like, and if the ſame die likewiſe, then take another, and ſo doe as aforeſaid, and let the partie grieued be applyed therewith as aforeſaid, as long as any of them doe die.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another excellent good Plaiſter to draw the ſore.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Camomill flowers</hi> and <hi>Mallow leaues,</hi> of each of them an handfull, and cut the <hi>Mallow leaues</hi> and the <hi>Camomill Flowers</hi> very ſmall and boyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them in faire running <hi>Water</hi> (but let the water be more then an inch aboue the hearbes) and let them boyle vntill the water be almoſt conſumed: Then put therein 2. ounces of <hi>Lynſeede,</hi> beaten t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fine powder d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. an handfull of Wheaten <hi>Howe,</hi> 2. ounces of <hi>Oyle</hi> of <hi>Roſes,</hi> and 3. or 4. ounces of <hi>Swines Greaſe,</hi> (the ſcum being taken away) and temper them well together, and then ſet them ouer a ſoft fire, without any ſmoke,, and ſtir them very well with a ſticke, and ſo let them boyle together, vntill you perceiue the water be quite conſumed: Then take them off the fire and beate them well together in a Morter, vntill you ſee them well incorporated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and in féeling to be ſmoothe and not rough: Then take a parſell thereof, and heate it either in a Porrenger, or elſe in ſome Earthen diſh vpon a Chafing-diſh of Coales, and then ſpread it thicke vpon a fine linnen cloth, or elſe vpon a peece of Leather, and ſo apply it to the ſore, and this will draw it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your owne deſire. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20617:13"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a new Loafe of <hi>Bread,</hi> and lay it to the fore as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> may poſſibly be ſuffred, as it commeth forth of the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and afterwards let it be bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t or elſe buried in the Earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> elſe take leaues of <hi>Scabious</hi> or <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rell</hi> roaſted, or elſe 2. or 3. <hi>Lill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> rootes</hi> roaſted vnder the embers, and applyed to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all theſe are good to ripen the ſore.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A very good Plaiſter to draw the Plague ſore to a head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to breake it.</head>
                  <p>TAke 2. handfuls of <hi>Mallowes,</hi> 1. handfull of <hi>Linſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed,</hi> a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of ſowre <hi>Dow,</hi> and 2. or 3. <hi>Lilly rootes,</hi> and ſtamp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> theſe together very ſmall, and boyle them in a quart of <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Lees,</hi> vntill it be thicke, then lay it on inch thicke or more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a piece of Leather, that is ſomewhat broader then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and let the borders of the Leather be plaiſtred with ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers waxe, and that will cauſe it to cleane faſt, and this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> bring forth the Botch, and breake it in a very ſhort ſpace. <hi>This hath beene truely proued.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another Plaiſter to draw the ſore.</head>
                  <p>TAke a ſpoonefull of <hi>Hunny,</hi> 2. or 3. ſpoonfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls of the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yce of <hi>Spurge,</hi> a ſpoonefull of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and a good quantitie of wheaten <hi>Hower,</hi> and temper them well together without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fire, and make thereof a Plaiſter, and lay it to the ſore, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the end of euery 14. houres renew the Plaiſter, and this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> draw it wonderfull much.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke 2. handfulls of <hi>Scabious,</hi> and ſtampe it in a Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> then temper it well with two ounces of <hi>Swines g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eaſe,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is ſalted, and the <hi>Yolke</hi> of an <hi>Egge,</hi> then ſtampe them al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and it will draw it excéeding well.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
